[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a Madhyamanikaya 82, and it's a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just read out this discussion that's happening between Venerable Ratapada and a certain king at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this king describes four kinds of lusts
[SPEAKER_01]: That a person can go through, and then on account of that, would ordain as a monk, go forth as a holy man.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he points out that Venerable Ratpāla has not experienced those losses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why has he ordained?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he replies, I went forth because he understood these four summaries of the dhamma taught by the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they're old, they've got nothing more to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They... loss of health, they get sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Loss of wealth and loss of relatives.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... and... Venerable Ratapala describes these, why he went forth, on account of these four summaries of the Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Number one is
[SPEAKER_01]: Life in any world is unstable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which kind of relates to that aging, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are aging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are falling apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, but I mean unstable in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Your old age is not guaranteed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may not live that long.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you said so many times before, I don't know from what book that quote is, but
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you're born, you're old enough to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Heidegger was quoting it from somebody else, if I remember correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, yeah, as soon as there is a manifestation, implication of death is there at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: The implication of cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you are 10, 20, 60 years old, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: That implication is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if somebody becomes aware of that, you realize, oh, yeah, no, that is the reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, life is unstable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that whole Hindu idea of four stages of life, whereby the only last stage is when you go forth and that's how you get most of the whole life, it's completely based on these assumptions that you will reach the old age and that your faculties will be working in the old age and you won't be kind of affected by illness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just basically a worldly idea of trying to squeeze as much as they can out of sensuality and then go and practice the holy life, failing to understand that the longer you stay
[SPEAKER_00]: Not practicing the holy life, the more of a burden you accumulate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were not able to go against the grain and give up the burden when there wasn't so much burden accumulated, you're not going to be able to do it when you were 60 with, like, you know, a lot of burden in your mind of... and I mean burden in terms of, like, you know, attachments, habits, views, assumptions, control, sense of mastery,
[SPEAKER_00]: sense of mind, all of that proliferates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a static thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The habits.
[SPEAKER_00]: The habits, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ferment, proliferate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, even these small mundane habits are quite a lot for people, but let alone, you know, the ones that your kind of life depends on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding that life is unstable, in itself, is more than enough to try and do something about it, if you truly understand the way
[SPEAKER_00]: Aging is not when you turn 60.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aging is already this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you are already aging, and you are already heading towards that disintegration of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not guaranteed that you're gonna see the, you know, 80, 90 year old age or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because manifestation is there, means possibility of death is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it feels like I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of discernment, it's a very perilous game.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, putting off these things that you... you know... You surely do know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to sort this out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll do it later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me get the most out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... well, that's... that's smarter talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this second summary of the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_01]: Life in any world has no shelter and no protector.
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems to relate to the illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like, you know, when Buddha compares it like you should not allow your consciousness to rest upon anything as a safe space, safe place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only safe place is complete cessation and dispassion and abandoning of everything, this life, everything, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Humanity
[SPEAKER_00]: Love, attachments, things that are dear to you, all of that is a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what the Buddha was actually teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very different from what people think the Buddha was teaching, you know, world peace and loving-kindness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one mind is safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, nothing, nothing is safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, compared, what is it, compared consciousness to the whip, like being hit with a whip.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the spears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, with the spears, yeah, the spears, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The contact was a whip.
[SPEAKER_00]: Similar to where... yeah, so each time your consciousness gets established upon something, you should regard it as being struck with a spear, because that's the peril of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's truly nothing to regard as suitable to rest upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: No safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: No safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only safety is that cessation of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Complete removal of this passion,
[SPEAKER_00]: And pretty much any appreciation of life or anything within it, it needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, disenchantment, revulsion, all those things the Buddha was describing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can, you can, yeah, try and be...
[SPEAKER_00]: So that the mind turns away, and completely lets go of any need for safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because need for safety is based on the wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's based on the sense of ownership,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, the need to protect what's mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Need to find a safe space for what's mine, where it will be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as you're seeking some safety, you're implying some ownership of something you want to be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus, you won't be safe because of that very thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That vulnerability.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are vulnerable because you take things as... Well, you take things that are not yours, as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're in debt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're vulnerable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Māra has access to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The third summary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Life in any world has nothing of its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: One has to leave all and pass on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you ever gained it, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you ever secured it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, again, even like, oh, this is mine...
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember, I think we spoke about it a while ago, in one of the talks, like, even the notion of things that belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to start, you know, breaking them with a hammer to prove that you're not the owner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just start... just make the effort and understand what do you mean, like, for yourself, when you say, oh, this item, this is mine, this belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that belonging entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how does it feel in a way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is it as a phenomenon?
[SPEAKER_00]: That belonging of something to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean you're in its control?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean you're its creator?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean you... it cannot be taken away?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that ownership imply?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize that that's the trick of the ownership is
[SPEAKER_00]: The power of the ownership is that people don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just kind of skate on top of it, take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, mine, mine, mine, mine, mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even without any Buddhist practice, if a mind would just stop and think about it, like, what does it mean when something is mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how would I describe that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the properties of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize the contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certainly, it would help you not take
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that are yours, so much is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: They wouldn't be as much yours, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize, well, yeah, the notion of mine, it's quite relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's mine for as long as that thing is there, but I have no fundamental say in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's mine for as long as I'm there, but I have no fundamental say in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, okay, it's relatively mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I'm the current user of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by not thinking about that, what does mine mean, they do take it in that kind of infinite sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why always that infinite threat of when something mine is threatened to be taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you stop and think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I don't care much about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I care that mine is attacked.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mine is under a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I never questioned the notion of mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I take it in an infinite sense, ultimate sense, that mine means mine forever and must stay and be protected that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's even like, again, even further contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it were yours, you wouldn't need to protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it were in your control, it would not be under any threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could not be under a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were the master of its existence, it would listen only to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that's the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, people go around with the attitude, mind belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you can only... that's the way, you know, that's where passion is, you know, you can't have passion for something if it's not really yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really matter, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's, yeah, if you start questioning that notion of mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are already narrowing down, I suppose you could say, the basis for proliferation of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are diminishing passion, in simple terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: By questioning the notion of mind, you are diminishing passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be unlikely to be trying to get things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Striving really hard to get things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not be...
[SPEAKER_00]: As gripped by that kind of blind ambition, without any context of its ultimate relativity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, and relativity, I mean, exactly, yeah, yeah, I work for it, I earned it, it's mine, I built it, I created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That still doesn't mean that it cannot be taken away and that it won't be taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what Venerable Rūpa Pāla says is, fundamentally, from that ultimate point of view of, you know, life and death, pretty much,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're able to re-evaluate your investments.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not acting out of this assumption that you will live forever and that your possessions will carry on even after you die or something, my legacy and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly inconceivable as a motivator for action and, you know, and provider of ambition.
[SPEAKER_00]: That won't be possible because ambition and action of that kind, it basically always has to be rooted in passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes things easier, doesn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm only here for a little while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I need to have all these requisites?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, do I have to have the most exquisite house?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if the context is sustained, then life becomes easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sustaining the context is what's not easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or building it up, that's what's not easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not natural to go against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you invest the effort to develop wisdom in that context, then, yeah, life will be much easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you will be less able to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't have so much passion in your mind that binds you to things gratuitously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they change, you will not be affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the definition of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind doesn't know anything other than the ownership of the senses, of the body, and everything else that has proliferated through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: My house, my family, my friend, my reputation, my name, my business, my savings, my this, my this, my this, my this, my all this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Burdened by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All, exactly, all of that is burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: While it's falling apart, you just
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fourth summary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Life in any world is incomplete, insatiable, the slave of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there is no... there's no satisfaction, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just appeasing the hungry animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only sort of suppress the hunger until it comes back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that cannot end on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So hunger cannot end simply by providing food for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: of the craving in life is not the satisfaction, it's perpetuation of itself, not the satisfaction of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the hunger perpetuates itself through eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you ate, you get hungry again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you eat, and then you get hungry again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no other nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no other reality to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same goes with the thirst, of craving, the taṇha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... there is no
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a mental attitude towards scratching the itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the attitude that determines the, you know, the desire, the craving, the insufficient, I want this, I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Itch in itself doesn't... neither need scratching nor not scratching.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just an itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hunger in itself does not need food.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the mental attitude that sees the outcome of food as pleasurable,
[SPEAKER_00]: is what's dependent on that, is what gives meaning to the hunger and keeps acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same with the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you see feeling for what it is, painful feeling as painful feeling, nothing more, nothing less, agreeable feeling as agreeable feeling, nothing more, nothing less, and neutral feeling as neutral feeling, nothing more, nothing less, the attitude of mind affected with craving will be adding meaning to that through
[SPEAKER_00]: That further assumption, further need, further pressure, further thirst and hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is, in itself, like a vicious circle that perpetuates itself infinitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the life in itself, in any realm, wherever else, wherever else it is, it's completely insatiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in itself, it just provides a fuel for itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of craving, basically, in an unpleasant feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you provide fuel for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the pleasant feeling is present, stop acting out of it for more of it, because that's how you provide fuel for that craving, for more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that... because, yeah, pleasant feeling is just pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, it doesn't matter how pressing an itch might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressing side of an itch is your mental attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, itch
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not need a scratch.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it's meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for another hand, in the seen, there's just the seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the heard, there's just the heard, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could even say in the felt, there's just felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: In perceived, it's just perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there are no more gratuitous assumptions in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any mental pleasure or pain that arises on its own, in itself, is enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's never enough for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never enough for the mind that's taking it as mine, that carries the assumption of more or less.
[SPEAKER_00]: More, if it's pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption of more, immediate.
[SPEAKER_00]: When pleasure is present, the assumption of more of it is immediately there.
[SPEAKER_00]: When pain is present, the assumption of less is immediately there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it will never be enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you're interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you provide a fuel for
[SPEAKER_00]: It's insatiable because you created the notion of satiability.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the notion of satiability, it's completely enough in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not insatiable anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It never was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're... so, it's that idea that I... if I go after these feelings, I try to... See, going after these feelings already implies they're somehow not enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or there's somehow too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm looking for... And that's your assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the feeling, but that's your craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to what end?
[SPEAKER_01]: For...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want completion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to feel... That's always kind of that kind of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to feel whole, but failing to understand that you are the one creating the division to begin with, by acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to feel, yeah, stable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't act out, if you do allow ownership to dissipate and kind of evaporate, so if you truly
[SPEAKER_00]: experience letting go of things, then things are already sufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the scene, there's just the scene.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: A whole picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing to be insatiable there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only thing that there was insatiable there was your own attitude, basically, that you projected onto things being insufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was just your attitude gratuitously resisting or gratuitously welcoming those feelings and